A Guide to the Papers of Don Marquis 1917-1934
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Don Marquis, 1917-1934
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7887
This collection consists of 33 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given the the Library on April 13, 1965.
Scope and Content Information
The papers, 1917-1934, of Donald Robert Perry Marquis contain manuscripts for fifteen stories, plays, poems, and an outline. Letters to various publishers, editors, writers, actors, and directors chiefly concern Marquis's creative endeavors. He solicits the opinions of Robert Bridges, Vincent McCafferty and William Lingel on several pieces. In other letters Marquis encourages young writers, describing the influence of his journalism career and giving advice on marketing poetry. He explains why the "Evening Sun" dismissed H. L. Pangborn and regrets his failure to review Christopher Morley's "Shandygaff". Personal letters convey news of family, finances and health and ideas for novels.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - "As Thomas Might Have Seen It" n.d., TMsS, 3 p. on 3 1.
    Signed with comments by Don Marquis
  - "Bogumil Dawison" n.d., TMsS, 19 p. on 15 l.
    Signed with corrections and several autograph pages or sectons. AMs on back of 5 and 6: Unrelated poem: "As It Looks to Archy."
  - "Bogumil Dawison" n.d., TMs, 3 p. on 3 l.
    Incomplete Text with autograph corrections
  - "Bogumil Dawison" n.d., TMs, 7 p. on 7 l.
    Text with autograph corrections and additions
  - "Bogumil Dawison" n.d., TMs, 11 p. on 11 l.
    Text with autograph corrections
  - Poem: "A Certain Club" n.d., TMs, 2 p. on 2 l.
    Includes carbon copy
  - "Dogs and Boys" n.d., TMs, 23 p. and 23 l.
    Autograph corrections 1-9 and 12, remainder in autograph; sketch of dog on last page
  - "Floretta Crashes the Movies" n.d., TMs, 16 p. on 16 l.
  - Poem: "History of Life" n.d., AMs, 4 p. on 2 l.
  - "Mayme" n.d., TMsS, 10 p. on 10 l.
    Signed with autograph corrections
  - "Mr. Piffle's Ghosts" n.d., TMsS, 17 p. on 17 l.
    Signed but with erased signature; with autograph corrections
  - Poem: "Ragnarok was out of luck - - -" n.d., AMs, 12 p. on 12 l.
  - Poem: "Technocracy" n.d., AMs, 11 p. on 11 1.
    With 3-page carbon typescript uncorrected
  - "Notes on Being Fat" n.d., AMs, 3 p. on 3 l.
  - Outline: "Story About Klan" n.d., AMs, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Miscellaneous Notes n.d., AMs, 2 p. on 2 l.
- Letters
  - Editor of Ladies Home Journal (?) to D.M. 1917 Sept 28, TL, 1 p.
    Writer expresses his interest in including the poem "A Women's if" that appeared in the Sun Dial a year ago, signed F. H. H. on the "That Reminds Me" page and questions D.M. as to its author. Says he has sent "Willie Applewhite" to Churchill Williams of The Saturday Evening Post for his consideration.
  - D.M. to Mr. Skiff 1918 March 7, ALS, 1 p.
    Will be glad to autograph the books.
  - D.M. to to [Christopher] Morley [1918] May 28, TLs, 1 p.
    Signed and with autograph comments by H. L. Pangborn, Dana Burnett and Winfield S. Moody. The editors apologize for letting the Evening Sun go to press without mention of his book, Shandygaff.
  - D.M. to Don C. Seitz 1919 October 17, ALS, 3 p.
    Thanks Mr. Seitz for lending him his copy of "Reuben Davidger (?)." Mentions the letters of recommendation he and Mr. Moody are writing to Mr. Seitz and Mr. Cobb regarding H. L. Pangborn. Explains the reasons behind Pangborn's recent dismissal as an editor at The Evening Sun.
  - D.M. to Mr. Johnson 1922 June 20, TLS, 2 p.
    Autograph postscript in D.M.'s hand dated July 1. Thanks Mr. Johnson, Dr. Van Dyke, and Mr. (Irving Addison) Bacheller for asking him to join the Author's Club. Requests that he delay presenting his name to the board until October because of his present financial condition due to just buying a house. Says he owes a debt of gratitude to Dr. Johnson for his recognition as a serious poet.
  - D.M. to Murray Phillips 1927 May 13, TLS, 1 p.
    Compliments Mr. Phillips on his revival of "Kempy" at the Hudson Theatre as well as the performances of both Elliot Nugent and "the Senior Nugent." Suggests that Mr. Phillips consider reviving "The Old Soak" with D. M. in the leading part.
  - D.M. to Mr. Sinsabaugh 1927 October 1, TLS, 5 p.
    Comments on style and saleability of Mr. Sinsabaugh's story, "Henry." Atlantic Monthly, The Bookman, and Outlook are more likely to express an interest than Saturday Evening Post or Liberty, he believes. Discusses what to expect as a writer from the publishing industry. Advises him on story craft and formula with lengthy examples. "Who? What? When? Where? and Why?" are questions, he says, that every good story must address. Discusses his years as a journalist.
  - D.M. to Robert Bridges 1928 January 21, TLS, 2 p.
    Requests permission to include stories contributed to Scribner's Magazine in a book to be published by Doubleday, Doran and Company next autumn. Compliments Mr. Bridges on Scribner's new type. Relates his exasperation with the theatre company he has been working with for eight months and tells him he has no new short fiction to send him. Asks if R. B. will be interested in a novel he will finish in about eight months. Discusses the novel's predominant theme (theology) and literature in general.
  - [R.B.] to D.M. n.y. or [1928 ?] January 26, TL (carbon), 1 p.
    R. B. grants D. M. permission to use the stories that Scribner's Magazine published in 1927 in his collection. Expresses his interest in D. M.'s novel in progress, complimenting him on his good characterization.
  - D.M. to R.B 1928 Feb 15, TLS, 1 p.
    Requests information on total money paid to him by Scribner's in 1927. Explains that he needs the information for income tax purposes.
  - [R.B.] to D.M 1928 Feb 16, TL (carbon), 1 p.
    In response to his letter, R. B. informs D. M. that he was paid $2,250 for his stories, "A Keeper of Tradition," "The Flea, the Pup and the Millenium," and "O'Meara, the Mayflower and Mrs. MacLirr," @ $750 each.
  - D.M. to R.B. 1928 Mar 21, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that he is enclosing a story for his consideration for publication in Scribner's Magazine. The story, he says ("Getting a Show On") was written with Collier's Magazine in mind but returned to him because of its length.
  - [R.B.] to D.M. 1928 Mar 27, TL (carbon), 1 p.
    Enjoyed his story ("Getting a Show On") and regrets that its concern with the production aspects of small theatres is not general enough for his readers. The magazine is inundated with accepted fiction.
  - D.M. to Miss O'Brien 1930 Jul 23, ALS, 6 p.
    Compliments Miss O'Brien on the verses she has sent him. Encourages her to keep sending her work off and in the meantime he suggests that she contact John Gallishaw or Edmund Leamy. Informs her of the Bulletin which can be secured from the Author's League listing magazines and publisher.
  - D.M. to William Lingel 1934 Nov 12, TLS, 1 p.
    Requests a quick decision on his submission to Liberty Magazine so he can send it off to others.
  - D.M. to Vincent McCafferty 1934 Dec 19, TLS, 1 p.
    Sends story which has been turned down by Saturday Evening Post and Collier's Weekly to see if McCafferty can use it. Note on assignment sheet indicates this letter refers to "Floretta Crashes the Movies."
  - D.M. to C.[M.] n.y. Sep 23, TLS, 2 p.
    Writes that he has Morley's book and will say something about it in his column. Also that he has two half finished novels that he doesn't find time to finish. He mentions in the letter Walnut, Bureau County, Illinois, his newspaper column and his children.
  - D.M. to C.[M.] n.d., ALS, 1 p.
    Asks if he will lend him his scrap book of columns.
  - D.M. to [Conrad Milliken] n.d., TLS, 1 p.
    Mentions his misfortunes of the last 7 or 8 months. Expresses his gratitude for friends like Oliver, David, and Bill Footner.
- Miscellaneous
  - Bears autograph handwriting by D.M. n.d., Envelope
    Notes on his play that he needs help in producing. Mentions someone's wife, Reina, the Lord's Prayer and the Twenty Third Psalm.